# Shruthi Hiremath

Updated on July 23, 2024

Computational Behavior Analysis Lab,

School of Interactive Computing, Georgia Institute of Technology, 756 W Peachtree St NW,

Atlanta, GA 30308

Email: shiremath9@gatech.edu; hiremath.shruthi@gmail.com

Mobile: +1-470-265-163

Website Google Scholar

### Research Interest

My research interest broadly focuses on building novel activity recognition pipelines for nearable sensing devices. I focus on activity monitoring in smart homes, by observing data collected from residents in smart homes using nearable sensors. As such I propose a "lifespan" of a human activity recognition system in smart homes, which includes (a) initial bootstrapping procedure - aimed at 'jump-starting' the activity recognition system in the home, with minimal supervision from the resident; (b) updating and extending the activity recognition system - aimed at improving the recognition capabilities of the initial bootstrapped system; (c) routine assessment - aimed at behavior monitoring of residents over extended periods of observation.

### Education

Aug '18 - Dec '24 (expected)	Ph.D. in Computer Science	Atlanta, GA
•	Georgia Institute of Technology	
	Thesis: "Deriving Bespoke Human Activ-	
	ity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes"	
	Doctoral Committee: Thomas Plötz	
	(Advisor), Sonia Chernova, Diane Cook,	
	Gregory Abowd, Uichin Lee	
Aug '15 - May '17	M.S. in Computer Science	Atlanta, GA
	Georgia Institute of Technology	
Aug '10 - July '14	<b>B.Tech</b> in Computer Science	Vellore, India
	VIT UNIVERSITY	

## **Publications**

Refereed Conference, Journal and Workshop Papers

- P1. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2024). Game of LLMs: Discovering Structural Constructs in Activities using Large Language Models. Arxiv (Under Review).
- P2. Sourish Dhekane, Megha Thukral, **Shruthi K. Hiremath**, Harish Haresamudram and Thomas Plötz.(2024). Layout Agnostic Human Activity Recognition in Smart Homes through Textual Descriptions Of Sensor Triggers (TDOST). Arxiv (Under Review).

- P3. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2024).Maintenance Required: Updating and Extending Bootstrapped Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes. The 6<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Activity and Behavior Computing (ABC).
- P4. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2023). The Lifespan of Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes. Sensors 2023, 23(18), 7729; DOI: 10.3390/s23187729
- P5. Shruthi K. Hiremath, Yasutaka Nishimura, Sonia Chernova and Thomas Plötz.(2022). Bootstrapping Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes from Scratch. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT), 6(3), 1-27; DOI: 10.1145/3550294
- P6. Yulai Cui, **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz (2022). ROAR: Reinforcement Learning Based Online Active Learning for Human Activity Recognition. In 2022 International Symposium on Wearable Computers (ISWC) (pp. 2327); DOI: 10.1145/3544794.3558457
- P7. Mindy Scheithauer, **Shruthi K. Hiremath**, Audrey Southerland, Agata Rozga, Thomas Plötz, Chelsea Rock, Nathan Call (2022). Feasibility of accelerometer technology with individuals with autism spectrum disorder referred for aggression, disruption, and self-injury. Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders, 98, 102043; DOI: 10.1016/j.rasd.2022.102043
- P8. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz. (2021). On the Role of Context Length for Feature Extraction and Sequence Modeling in Human Activity Recognition. In 2021 International Symposium on Wearable Computers (ISWC) (pp. 13-17); DOI: 10.1145/3460421.3478825
- P9. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2020). Deriving effective human activity recognition systems through objective task complexity assessment. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT), 4(4), 1-24; DOI: 10.1145/3432227
- P10. Shruthi K. Hiremath, Pallavi Chandra, Anne M. Joy, and B. K. Tripathy (2015). Neighborhood rough set model for knowledge acquisition using MapReduce. International Journal of Communication Networks and Distributed Systems (IJCNDS), 15(2-3), 212-234; DOI: 10.1504/IJC-NDS.2015.070975
- P11. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Govinda K( 2014). Rainfall Prediction Using Artificial Neural Network. International Journal Applied Engineering Research, 9, (pp. 21243-21254).

## **Professional Experience**

#### Aug '18 - Present

### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Georgia Institute of Technology

I developed data-driven technologies for wearable and nearable based application scenarios to build deployable human activity recognition systems, with a focus on providing health monitoring.

#### May - July '16

#### **Data Science Intern**

ADP

My work involved development of data analysis procedures to analyze and gather insights from collected payroll data.

#### Aug '14 - July '15

## Software Developer

Deloitte USI (Hyderabad, India)

I was involved in building a tool that served as an interface between end users and project management activities (PMC) aimed as reducing the number of manual tickets raised for changes to a project team. The tool successfully contributed to a 70% reduction in costs associated with handling tickets, thereby achieving significant cost savings.

# Teaching Experience

### Teaching Assistant

	reaching Assistant	
Summer	CS 6601: Artificial Intelligence	Georgia Institute of
'19, '20, '21		TECHNOLOGY
Summer '22	CS 7470: Mobile & Ubiquitous Computing	Georgia Institute of
		TECHNOLOGY
Fall '16, '17	CS 4400: Database Systems	Georgia Institute of
		Technology

## **Funding**

2010

2020

2019 - 2020	Georgia	Cimicai	and	1ran	Siationai	Science
	Alliance	Grant	(PI:	Dr.	Thomas	Plötz),

Commis Clinical and Thomslational Science

\$15,000 [Read More].

Optimizing context length for improved ac-Lead Researcher

tivity recognition in wearable sensing.

2018 - 2019 Pilot Grant from NIH via Georgia Institute

of Technology (PI: Dr. Thomas Plötz)

Analyzing the feasibility of using acceleromenters to identify episodes of server behavior in youth on the Autism Spectrum Disor-

der (ASD)

2022 - 2024 Collaboration with KDDI Corporation (PI:

> Thomas Plötz and Dr. Dr. Sonia

Chrernova)

Novel Human-in-the-Loop Learning for re- LEAD RESEARCHER

alization of real-world AI

LEAD RESEARCHER

# Awards and Recognitions

2023	N <sup>2</sup> Women Young Research Fellowship (\$1000),
	Percom 2023
2022	Student Travel Grant (\$500), Ubicomp 2022 (by
	Georgia Institute of Technology)
2021	N <sup>2</sup> Women Young Research Fellowship (\$1000),
	Ubicomp 2021
2019	Imlay pre-proposal selected, Georgia Tech
2015, 2018, 2021	Grace Hopper Scholar, Georgia Tech
2014	Merit Scholar VIT University

# **Invited Talks**

2024	Maintenance Required: Updating and Extending Bootstrapped Human Activity Recognition Sys- tems in Smart Homes @ ABC (International Con- ference on Activity and Behavior Computing)
2022	ROAR: Reinforcement Learning Based Online Active Learning for Human Activity Recognition @ Ubicomp
2022	Bootstrapping Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes from Scratch @ Ubicomp
2021	Deriving effective human activity recognition systems through objective task complexity assessment  @ Ubicomp
2021	On the Role of Context Length for Feature Extraction and Sequence Modeling in Human Activity Recognition @ Ubicomp
2018	Detecting severe behavior episodes in youth on the Autism Spectrum Disorder @ Georgia Tech

# **Professional Service**

2018 - 2024	Reviewer ACM Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT)
2024	Ubicomp Posters and Demos
2024	UbiComp/ISWC 2024 Workshop on AI-infused Physical Systems
2024	Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (NordiCHI)
2023	Workshop on Ubiquitous and Multi-domain User Modeling (UMUM)
2022	International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (Percom)
2021	ACM Special Interest Group on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (SIGKDD)

Program Committee Member

2023 Served on the Program Committee for 'The Second Workshop on Ubiquitous and Multi-domain User Modeling (UMUM2023)'. Held in Conjunc-

tion with PerCom 2023. [Read More]

# **Community Service**

2018 - present	Mentor, Georgia Tech: mentored undergraduate
	and graduate student interested in research
2023	N <sup>2</sup> Women Event, Percom 2023
2022	Organizing Committee (Web Chair), Ubicomp
	2022
2021	N <sup>2</sup> Women Event, Ubicomp 2021
2020 - 2023	Social Chair, Ubicomp Lab @ Georgia Tech
2015 - 2022	Volunteer, India Club @ Georgia Tech
2010 - 2014	Core Member, Robotics Club @ VIT University